This video demonstrates how to perform the fundal reflex test.
Start with hand hygiene and introduce yourself.
Confirm the identity of the baby, explain the examination and gain consent to perform it.
The baby should be held securely and comfortably either on the lap or over a shoulder.
It's important for them to feel safe.
Start by asking if there are any concerns about general development,
eyesight or the appearance of the eyes, then make some observations.
Get a sense of the baby's general and
visual development by looking at the way they move, their tone and posture and
how well they
can fix on your face and eyes.
Move your head from side to side, increase your distance
and make silent smiles.
Take note of how steady fixation is, if they respond to your silent
smile and the distance at which they lose fixation.
At the same time look for any signs
of wobbly eyes, squint, red eye or white pupil.
Then prepare the arc light by selecting the
the brightest light setting with three clicks.
Make sure the lens rack is at the top where
there is no lens power in the sighthole.
Examination room needs to be quiet and dim.
Most babies
will naturally look at a light.
Get the sighthole close to your eye and at arm's length observe
the fungal reflex in both eyes at the same time.
Compare the brightness and colour between
the two eyes.
Look for any dark patches in the reflex or complete absence of the reflex.
trying to note the position of the corneal reflections.
The appearance will vary depending
on your distance from the baby and the angle of examination.
In a normal examination there
should be no overall difference in the brightness and colour between the two eyes
with the corneal
reflections appearing central.
This is a normal fundal reflex test of a white baby.
In non-white babies the colour of the fundal reflex is different.
The reflex tends to be
a paler with yellow, white, and even blue the main reflect in colors.
This is what the normal examination of a black baby looks like, and is
why this test is increasingly
called the fundal reflex test, rather than the misleading red reflex test.
Abnormal findings are when there is a persistent overall color or brightness difference between
the two eyes, a displaced corneal reflection, a dark patch present within the reflex of one
or both eyes, or a completely absent reflex.
To summarize, a normal examination is when there is no overall difference in the brightness
and colour between the two eyes, with central corneal reflections.
An abnormal fungal reflex is when there is a difference in the brightness and colour
between the two eyes, a displaced corneal reflection, a dark patch present within the
reflex of one or both eyes, or a completely absent reflex.
An abnormal
fundal reflex test can indicate the presence of cataract, retublastoma, corneal
scar, squint, refractive error, or a structural abnormality such as coloboa.
These all require further assessment by a specialist.
After the examination
repeat hand hygiene, thank the parent or care and document and explain your
findings.
Agree a clear plan for further assessment if needed.
Please have a look at our other
Universities and Andrews Arc Light project videos.